[Music]
good evening good day everyone
it's great to be back with you welcome
to episode
9 of ask abhijit today we discuss
geopolitics and great power competition
so to start off let me ask you a
question ask yourself this question
does india belong in the category of
great powers of great global powers
that's the question we need to ask
ourselves before we even
deal with this uh particular topic
so i have once again got amazing
questions from all of you i've got so
many questions i'm gonna have to do many
more episodes
of of the geopolitics discussion so i
have
chosen a bunch of your questions i hope
they are representative of
many of the questions that you you
people have asked several times
so without further ado without wasting
your time let's get into question number
one
so this is by keshav lada
sometimes it seems that the usa is
unpredictable
sometimes some days it will teach
democracy sometimes it interferes in
other countries matters
and sometimes it is dormant while we
know that china is expansionist so we
can predict its its geopolitical moves
how can we classify the form of
geopolitics of countries
and which form is the best
so what you are essentially asking is
what is geopolitics
and which form of geopolitics is the
best
so geopolitics is a sport
it is a sport that in which you make up
the rules as you go there are no
written rules nothing is set in stone
and the objective
of this sport is to basically
acquire world domination acquire control
over the resources
and territories and all the power and
influence that is available in the world
that is the sport of geopolitics there
are no written rules
there is something called international
law and all that
but that only applies to the weaker
nations
not the top-ranking global leaders right
the ones that indulge in great power
competition so the really powerful
nations such as the united states russia
china and some others sometimes these
nations
they write the rules as they go along
sometimes they will abide by the united
united nations resolutions
etc and sometimes they will break
whatever is whatever is called
international law
they do as they seem fit in pursuit of
certain
objectives so that is what we have to
understand
what is geopolitics what are the
objectives
the objectives like i said is to acquire
more territory more
power more influence control over
resources
but at the core of the matter
geopolitics is about the national
interest it is the pursuit
of the long-term national interest that
every country
is engaged in so that is what
geopolitics is now which form of
geopolitics is the best
so to answer this question let's compare
a few forms of geopolitics
the united states has been essentially
in the 20th century an imperialistic
power it has
spread its influence everywhere it has
military bases all
over the world it has a navy that sails
every single ocean in the world right it
has uh
soldiers and basically on every
continent
and it has had a part to play in almost
every war whether it is overt or covert
visible or invisible
so that is what the united states is so
it is
pursuing global domination that's what
it has done over the 20th century
the russians also did the same thing in
the 20th century
they also played the same game but not
as successfully as the
united states which is why the russians
which is why the ussr broke up as we
know very well and the chinese also
pursue that same game of uh relentless
expansion
and expansion not just uh of its
of its uh borders but also of its
influence
and its power and it does this by
various
means so this is what the united states
does what russia does and what
china does now let's compare that with
what
india's policy has been for since it was
since it
became an independent country in so
india's policy has been that of
non-alignment
we will not uh take any sides
but while saying that we are not aligned
we took the side of the
of the ussr right we did not pursue our
national interest we allowed ourselves
to become weaker
we pursued policies internal policies
that kept us
poor deliberately and uh we did not deal
with our
uh belligerent neighbors the way we
should have
so there is a different form of
geopolitics we always preach idealism
right india's track record has been of
of
sloganeering and talking about ethics
and morality
and having an idealistic foreign policy
in which you try to appease everybody
at your own expense so what form of
geopolitics is the best
well as you can see india has not
benefited
from this particular course of action
which has
which it has continued on for several
decades
so the best form of geopolitics is the
pursuit of our of
of one's national interest it is called
realism it's called real politic it has
nothing to do with
morality or or or ideologies or idealism
idealism it's only about the long-term
objectives you achieve them any which
way
you can the chinese have a saying it
doesn't matter whether the cat is black
or white
as long as it catches mice so that is
the way to approach geopolitics you need
to have an a certain
long-term objective in mind and then you
have to do whatever it takes
to reach there because at the end of the
day
a country's government and the country's
leader has only one
has only one responsibility it is to
serve
and protect the interests of the country
and its people
a leader's job is not to serve and
protect the interests of other countries
and other people because
they also have leaders who are doing
that so every leader every government
has to take care of its own internal
matters of its own national interest
and that is what geopolitics is supposed
to be like it's supposed to be the
pursuit of your national interest and
your national power
and to to understand that better you
have to understand what the national
interest is
so that's what we will get into uh
during the course of this discussion
so that is why the united states seems
to be unpredictable
that is why china behaves the way it is
the united states is not predictable
it is extremely predictable you can
always predict you can always tell that
it's going to follow its natural
interest
it's going to do what suit suits it best
and that is what the that is what
geopolitics is all about
so that i hope answers your question
let's go to the next question
vaishali asks in the world of
geopolitics who is india's most
trusted friend good question this is a
question
that many many indians have
and let me well explain what
things are like there are no friends
in geopolitics there are no friends
there are no enemies there are
allies and there are adversaries and
alliances
and adversarial engagements are always
temporary in nature nothing is permanent
nothing is set in stone
let me give you an example for the past
two and a half thousand years
ever since china became well ever since
china emerged as a civilization
two and a half thousand years ago all
this time india and china have
never had an adversarial relationship
never in the past two and a half
thousand years it's only after the
chinese communist party under mao citung
came to power in the 1950s
or thereabouts that india and china
became
adversaries the adversarial relationship
happened
because of chinese actions it started
with the conquest of tibet
the illegal annexation of tibet and then
they started having
designs on further indian territory so
this is the first time in two and a half
millennia
that india and china have become an
adversarial
uh relationship so for for the longest
time india and china were very good
not neighbors because tibet was always
the common neighbor
but now you have this situation let's
take another example
india and russia like i said india
officially was non-aligned but
unofficially and for all real intents
and purposes it was an
ally and a satellite of the soviet union
during the so-called
cold war now after the cold war ended
after the ussr disintegrated
a new republic was born russia the
russian union
russian republic and relations the
relationship between india and russia
hasn't been
the way the india ussr relationship was
this relationship is not black and white
it's not straightforward
it is not a straightforward
relationship it is complicated as
as we know russia is currently engaged
in
various other relationships with
countries such as
china and pakistan which india
would never have expected if it was the
cold war
so it russia indians always look upon
russia as a great friend
right but that was a relationship that
was mutually beneficial at that time
today russia finds benefit elsewhere it
still has a reasonably good relationship
with india
but it isn't the way it was right it
isn't unconditional
the way it was in the during the cold
war so things
change before 1947 there was no pakistan
so we did not have any issue
on the western border today we have this
issue because this new temporary nation
exists there currently
and so on and so forth so there are no
friends okay once again
we talk about israel and indians love
israel
israel is our bosom buddy or great
friend
india and israel have shared interests
and that is why the relationship is so
good
india and israel are in in some ways in
a very similar
position in a very similar situation so
that is why
the interests of these two nations
converge to a great deal
and and that is why there is such a
great amount of cooperation
between the two nations things can
change in the future
right so there is nothing permanent in
geopolitics there are no friends
or enemies there are temporary alliances
and temporary
temporary adversarial relationships if
we understand this then we will be able
to
see the world for what it really is it
is a transient place
in geopolitics the smallest unit of time
is the decade
nothing happens year after year okay the
the if you want to see
change on the geopolitical level you
have to see it decade by
decade and if you see it that way then
you will see how how
the alliances and even borders
change from time to time so that is the
lens through which we must look upon
geopolitics
it is the realistic lens lens not the
idealistic lens we have to be realistic
and pragmatic and recognize the fact
that every nation has its own
interests and when interests converge
we're gonna work together
when interest diverge we're gonna either
drift apart or even become
adversaries so that's how it works
next question
and mole asks will china
be the next hegemonic power in the next
50 years good question so it's all about
understanding what china is and what
china aspires to be
so i would say that china has already
become
to some extent a hegemonic power it
already has
occupied the so-called south china sea
it claims
the whole the entirety of the region
even though there are so many other
countries that are competing claim
claims it does it on the basis of its
naval muscle
and military muscle it is riding rough
shot over japan
on the in the senkaku islands senkaku
not the oyu
and it is bullying the philippines is
bullying every single
uh nation with which it has a common
border it's even gone to the extent of
trying to claim vladivostok
from the russians so that is what china
is doing and not just this bullying
because of its economic and military
muscle
it has infiltrated over time step by
step in a systematic manner
every single global institution such as
the united united nations the
world health organization and much more
so today china
can run its writ anywhere it wants
that's the
status it has already achieved it has
laid
dead traps on many poor nations it has
entangled the western nations in these
economic and uh mercantile webs
it has infiltrated the united states
hollywood is
essentially an organ a propaganda organ
of china
the united states media is essentially
cow towing to china
it has refused to even question what's
happening inside china in the past
year and a half so china has already
achieved a significant degree of
hegemonity
so yes china aspires to be a hegemonic
power in the next 50 years
now i would like to go a little further
into this and try and let's try and
understand what china is like
so every nation has a certain character
and personality of it
of its own which is
which is predicated on its culture
essentially and civilization
and you will see these patterns of
behavior
with each nation over centuries so
russia has a very
very very uh distinctive
character as a nation and you can see
this over the past 1000 years
the chinese have a very distinctive
nation uh character as a nation
india the same and the uh arabic
world also so every culture has some
distinctive patterns that of behavior
that repeat over and over again
and here's the thing about china china
is
china is not has never been
a country with a great deal of military
prowess china is an
extremely conservative nation it is
extremely averse to risk taking
and that is something you see over the
centuries and over the past 2000 years
china has fought many great wars and
let me point this out my friends all of
these great wars that china has fought
have been civil wars they have been
fought within various
chinese dynasties and and kingdoms and
empires
and they have led to shocking loss of
life
in the orders of in the order of tens of
millions of human lives lost
and that is a pattern that recurs over
history again and again
its major wars are within these are
civil wars
china is extremely extremely reluctant
to fight wars outside its territories
and whenever
it has been invaded by a strong power
china has invariably
lost and become occupied china was
occupied
by tibet in the 8th century the tibetans
captured
the capital of china and nobody knows
this today
right the japanese kept uh conquered
most of china
about a hundred years less than a
hundred years ago the mongols
i have spoken about this at length the
mongols took over china and established
the yuan dynasty there
and much more whenever a strong power
has
invaded china and brought the battle on
chinese soil
the chinese have always lost the chinese
will bully
only weak nations china is extremely
reluctant to fight real wars
and sometimes it bites its bite off it
bites off too much
much more than it can chew in the 19
in in 1967 it tried to repeat 1962 with
india
and it lost that war which our media in
our textbooks will not
tell us about india beat china in the
1967 war
and in 1979 if i am not mistaken
china tried to invade vietnam it was a
disastrous defeat
at the hands of vietnam so the chinese
have a very very patchy and
inglorious military history they will
bully you when you're weak
that's what they did to india in 1962
the moment you take the
battle on their own soil the chinese
defenses invariably crumble
and this is something the world needs to
recognize so
china's hegemony is non-military china
is building a lot of military muscle
but it hopes to never have to go to war
it hopes to never have to fight
anything except a small power like the
philippines or taiwan
it doesn't ever want to fight a great
power and that's the thing about china
the military muscle is for the sake of
deterrence only
it will never dare fight russia it will
never dare fight the united states
despite its its shrill rhetoric
so we have to understand these things
about china there's a great deal more
than meets the eye
so that's a so the chinese hegemony is
basically predict predicated on its
economic muscle
on the visible military muscle that it
has acquired
on the technologies that it is acquiring
it has bought technologies big
technologies stolen technologies
it is now one of the technological
giants in the world
it is especially advanced in the field
of cyber warfare
it is a very good space program it has
lots of military
satellites it's launched more than 20
satellites this year most of them are
spy satellites so china is investing in
the future it's investing in future
hegemony but it
intends to never fight a kinetic war the
third world war
will not be kinetic in nature it will be
something very different
so china yes unless something untoward
happens something
that they have not planned unless
something like that happens china will
most likely be the next hegemonic power
in the next 50 years because the united
states is
receding as a power it is beset by
internal troubles
it has lost its moorings it has lost its
uh
appetite for expansion like it had in
the 20th century
so unless something uh something
unexpected happens from unexpected
quarters
china may very well become the hegemon
in the next 50 years
that's the answer
okay akash asks russia and china's
relationship has
strengthened should we be concerned
excellent question this deals with
russia and china russia and china have a
complicated relationship to say the
least
what you are actually asking is does
vladimir putin trust xi jinping
does russia trust china so that is the
issue we have to really look into
in order to answer this question so yes
right now russia and china seem to be
allies they are working together on
various global international forums
they have alliances in various places in
iran for example in pakistan
in afghanistan and many other places you
have the shanghai cooperation
organization some it's called something
like that
and they're cooperating on many other
fronts so there seems to be a great deal
of cooperation and work in
tandem between these two powers but
let's look
under the hood shall we because
if you know history if you study history
then it tells you much more than
what you can see at the surface level
today
so let's let's peel back the layers of
this relationship and let's just go back
less than a hundred years
let's uh so when china became uh
when mao zedong and the communist party
took over china they defeated the
komintan the komintang in chiang
kai-shek
exiled the common tank to taiwan so
that's when
mao became the undisputed supreme leader
of china the dictatorship of china
and mao zedong was greatly greatly
inspired by joseph
stalin so most of
aspired to be like joseph stalin and
acquire the
kind of power and um and untremeled
uh influence that
joseph stalin had so he hero worshiped
stalin
but stalin always treated mao zedong
like a junior colleague
right so that was the relationship
between mao and stalin after stalin died
i think it was nikita khrushchev who
came to power and
mao zedong and nikita khrushchev tried
to have a good relationship between the
two countries
but again the russians were way more
powerful and way larger than the chinese
and they always treated the chinese with
disdain so this
in brief led to something called the
sino-soviet split
so despite being marxist communist
socialist nations these two countries
drifted apart and they actually became
adversaries it came to the point that
russia
not under krishna but under brezhnev
even contemplated a nuclear strike on
the chinese because things were getting
out of control
so let me talk about the events of 1969
and let me do that
by showing you a map so let's go to this
map
we all know can you see my pointer
yeah you can see my pointer now so we
know where india is let's go eastwards
let's zoom in
this is occupied tibet and xinjiang we
go eastwards this is
china and this here
is russia if you can see my point of
this is russia present-day russia
and russia extends all the way down
south here to vladivostok which is just
north of north korea so in 1969
somewhere around here let me find the
region let me find the place
this is the boundary of russia and china
it is the yusuri river
this river forms the present boundary of
russia and china the present
international border
so in 1969 over here
at zhenbau island what is now known as
shenbau island
in 1969 this island was
in russian it was russian territory so
in 1969 the chinese
army launched a military raid on this
island and it killed dozens of russian
soldiers
and the russians retaliated killed many
more chinese and the nations were at war
it was an undeclared war
over this particular island
and things went so bad like like i said
the russians
even contemplated a nuclear strike on
china and this escalated much further
beyond this particular region
it went the the tension spilled over
to xinjiang so russia and china this is
as you can see it's north of india my
pointer is here
between mongolia and kazakhstan there's
a little
piece of land about 50 kilometers long
or so
which is the border between russia and
china over here also there was a border
clash
so the situation was very tense between
these two countries
it was kind of like what we have on the
india tibet border currently
so there were armed clashes people died
soldiers died
and things nearly went very bad
but then the americans intervened
and richard nixon threatened the
russians with war
if they nuked china so the americans
saved china from being nuked by the
russians
and this border dispute lasted for a
very long time between russia and china
the shenbao island was properly
demarcated this this region
in 1991 only and it was only in
1998 that russia and china finally
completely demarcated their border and
yet
china keeps raising issues with with the
border
it kind of recently tried to claim
vladivostok the port of vladivostok
so this situation under the hood is very
complicated it's quite tense there is a
lot of history
and there's a lot of a lot of bad blood
between russia and china
and you may not know this but russia has
pointed nuclear missiles in china
long-range ballistic nuclear missiles
and even on the stretch of border i
showed you between
in north of xinjiang russia has deployed
short-range iskandar ballistic missiles
nuclear ballistic missiles
and pointed them towards china as we
speak right now that is the situation
so should we can be concerned about the
russia china relationship
and the real question is does vladimir
putin trust xi jinping
so my question is do you think vladimir
putin trusts anybody
he does not vladimir putin is a hard
realist he does not trust china he
doesn't trust xi jinping
he knows that he's in a militarily
advantageous advantageous situation
compared to china he has an enormous
military
he has a military so strong that even
the americans are afraid of it
the disadvantage he has is that he has a
very long border
and a great amount of land that is
closer to china than
to moscow so this situation is still
very tense
despite external appearances i do not
see
russia and china having a good long-term
relationship it will eventually go south
again because china's ambition is to be
the sole
power the sole geopolitical power in the
world it will not countenance
a second power center anywhere and that
is what it's working towards
so eventually sooner rather than later
the relationship is going to turn
bad it's only a matter of time
but when that happens is to be seen will
it happen this decade or the next one
most likely for the for the time being
at least it's going to be a reasonably
good relationship
these next five or ten years at most and
then
as china gets more powerful russia will
feel threatened and you will see
something
happening something very interesting
happening
so that's your the answer to your
question that's a good question very
good question
bandit singh asks iran despite being a
hostile partner to indian interests
especially in kashmir
and hassan rouhani regularly demand
india on a global level
also went along very well with imran
khan
despite a bad relationship between
between iran and pakistan
what do i think how should india
approach the iranian question
especially when we are dependent on iran
being the center of the proposed trade
route from
mumbai to moscow this is an excellent
question
so that's the this is a very very
good question and right now you may have
heard the news that iran has entered
into an agreement with china
a long-term strategic agreement
which involves in the very significant
amount of chinese investment into iran
to the tune of
tens or hundreds of billions of dollars
and so that is the concern for india and
the media has been very vocal and shrill
about it
and the media has been saying that india
and iran are natural allies etc
so the indian government has messed up
by
by forcing the in the iranians into the
chinese hands
into china's arms so how much is the
truth to it so what is the relationship
between india and iran
so i like i said in the history sessions
india and iran
are essentially the same people we are
the same ethnicity
the persians came from india from from
the rig vedic
parshwa clan and so so they are
essentially
a descendant of ancient indians and for
a very long time india and persia had a
very good relationship
as cordial neighbors and like like
far away cousins and this started
changing about 1400 or so years ago with
the arabic
conquest of iran so iran was overrun by
the arabs in no time at all
it was a very quick and and
comprehensive conquest
and what happened very quickly in iran
was a complete change of culture
so the iranians became part of the the
sphere of influence of the arabs they
became part of the islamic world and
they essentially
looked up started looking upon india as
an alien culture
as a very different culture so this is
when the first
proper split between india and persia
happened and then
the relationship was not very good it
was rather antagonistic
the iranians used to be employed as uh
many iranians persians were employed by
the mughals
in their courts as administrators
officers etc
etc so they were essentially agents of
the foreign
foreign occupying force and then the
straw that broke the camel's bro that
broke the camel's back was nadar shah's
invasion of india in which he committed
unbelievable atrocities
he drenched delhi in a in a river of
blood
and took away a great deal of treasure
from delhi
so in the past thousand or sorry years
india and iran have had a reasonab
rather bad relationship iran
today the people of iran kind of look
upon india as
a country that was defeated in the past
as a conquered
land and a conquered people and there is
a sort of superiority complex to some
extent in some quarters
of iran now
let's look at iran geopolitically so so
the the
question of india and iran being natural
allies
doesn't arise on a cultural level at
least today the people of iran
are a very different culture they're
very nice people by the way very
friendly very
very good people but culturally they are
very different from the people of india
so the
natural allies argument doesn't really
hold now geopolitically what is iran's
conduct like what are their ambitions
what are the geopolitical ambitions
so let's look at how they have uh
conducted their affairs in the past
so they were once an american satellite
under muhammad musa
they were essentially being used for oil
by the americans
and then you had the shah pahlavi
masada was not an american it pahlavi
was an american puppet
musa was a i believe a democratically
elected leader of iran
who was overthrown and uh
became the king of iran he was an
american puppet then he was overthrown
by the
in the 1979 uh islamic revolution in
iran
when the ayatollahs came to power and
that is the regime that's currently in
iran
so iran is a very active geopolitical
player it has
despite its its uh relative small size
despite its small economy
despite being under incredible sanctions
it still has a strong military it has a
very powerful presence
outside his borders it is a very strong
spy agency
and it it interferes and tries to shape
the affairs of
of various nations there is a very
strong
iran and saudi arabia rivalry iran is a
very strong
undercover presence in iraq in syria
it's arming the houthis who are fighting
the saudis
so there is a presence in yemen as well
and
iran aspires to be a nuclear weapons
power
so this is a power this is a country
with oversized geopolitical ambitions
it essentially aspires to
resuscitate the accommodate
empire the empire it wants to become an
imperial power again
now imagine this country iran with
nuclear weapons
do you think it will behave in the same
nice way as it does today
hell no iran will be a very different
beast if it acquires nuclear weapons
nobody will be safe nobody in its
neighborhood will be safe from its
from being from having nuclear
weapons pointed at them not pakistan not
saudi arabia not
india and iran's geopolitical interests
are
in no way convergent with india's india
wants to be
a force of stability in asia india does
not want warfare and
and conflicts iran on the other hand has
been itching for conflict for the past
for the since 1979 it's been embroiled
in so many conflicts
some are open conflicts some are covered
conflicts so iran in a sense
engages in proxy wars everywhere it
behaves just like pakistan has been
behaving in kashmir
in other places so iran and india do not
have anything
in common almost the people of iran are
very nice
at the people-to-people level we we
still share a great deal with them but
on a
on a national geopolitical level iran
and india have
nothing in common it is by no means a
natural ally
the interests are very divergent right
now in iran
in the past two or three decades india
iran was trying to
uh cultivate a good relationship with
india for the sa
and sell oil to india so that it can get
some money and some cash
because it was desperately short of cash
but now that the chinese influx has
happened which was bound to happen
anyway
uh it has no more need for india so we
need to basically forget about chabahar
we need to find
other ways of expanding of of securing
our long-term national interests so this
is how india should approach iran
india should by no means see iran as a
trusted partner as a geopolitical ally
or like would like indians would say a
friend iran is not a friend
iran is pursuing its own independent
geopolitical
ambitions currently it is betting on
china because it is desperate
there are too many sanctions the chinese
are very happy to help out because it
helps their geopolitical ambitions so
like i said their interests
converge for the time being how long
will it last
will it last we don't know the iranians
have basically
sold out to the chinese and i wonder
what price they will end up paying
so once again to answer your question
iran and india
are not geopolitical they are not
natural geopolitical lies
we our interests don't align in any way
iran has always supported pakistan
historically and as we know kulbhushan
jadhav
was abducted from iran
and he was handed over to the pakistanis
so this again is kind of a backstab
if you see see the whole situation
properly
so india and iran can basically
to make it short india cannot trust iran
so that is the situation that's the
answer to your question
a very good question
this is by richie nair is it possible
for india to get back pok
pakistan occupied kashmir and aksai chin
which is
a part of ladakh that's currently
occupied illegally by china
if so what should india do to get back
our territories
china is trying to damp the himalayas
block water supply
is india doing enough this is important
considering the increase in water crisis
why is india not utilizing its
geographical position to strengthen the
navy and take control of the indian
ocean
all the way from east africa to
indonesia what should our leaders be
doing very good question sir
so let's deal with the first question
first p o k and aksai chin
so the best way to achieve certain
objectives
is to be patient and
desist from doing anything rash
oxide chain and pok have been in foreign
enemy hands for many decades there is no
need to try and grab it right now no
need to try and rush
it is indian territory it is legally and
historically
the territory that belongs to india's
civilization so we should regard it as
such but we should have a
long-term geopolitical plan that
stretches beyond aksai chin and pakistan
occupied kashmir
so if our objective if our sole
objective is to get back this little pok
at this
little oxide chin it is going to be
a very transient situation it may again
go back in the enemy hands
but if our ambition is to
free tibet from illegal chinese
occupation
then both the problems will be solved we
want a peaceful
northern border the border has always
been historically india and tibet it's
never been india china
so we want our sphere of influence back
it's not about our sphere of influence
it's about freeing the tibetan people
who have endured
decades of atrocious of incredible
atrocities and in cultural and other
genocide
at the hands of the chinese communist
party so india's long-term objective
over the next
10 to 20 years should be to engineer a
way of
freeing tibet of of restoring tibet to
its independence
which would cut the chinese off from the
from pakistan and kashmir and then we
would be able to deal with that
situation
separately the real threat the real
adversary that we have that india has
from an indian perspective
is not pakistan it is china china is the
real threat
and india needs to find a long-term
solution to deal with china and if we
are able to achieve that
then poke and accident and much more
will
revert to its historic civilizational
natural state
over over a reasonable period of time it
will not happen overnight
we need to plan for the next 20 years
and for the next 50 years and even for
the next 100 years
this is not a sprint this is a marathon
and we have to have the right kind of uh
uh
right kind of we have to understand this
this is not going to happen
overnight we have to have realistic
expectations
this is a multi-generation project to
restore india back to its
to its rightful civilizational status so
it is not going to happen tomorrow it's
not going to happen in the next five
years
maybe it will happen in the next 10 or
20 years if india plays its cards right
if the indian leadership behaves like a
real real leadership and has
ambitions for india on a civilizational
scale in on
in that case it will happen it is a
matter of time
now to answer your next question why is
india not utilizing its geographical
position to strengthen the navy and take
control of the indian ocean region
that's a very good question so let me
again show the geography here
okay where are we let me remove the
question
okay now you can see it better
so this is the indian ocean region can
you see the god
given position that india is in it
straddles this enormous piece of
naval real estate it is the gateway to
this
the east east of asia and to the west of
asia it can choke off
if it has a strong navy it can choke off
this straight over here the strait of
malacca it can even
influence uh what happens in the strait
of djibouti over here
so india is in a god-given geographical
position no country has such a beautiful
geographical position
and such an advantageous geographical
position from a naval
perspective and yet what are we doing
what sort of navy do we have
we have a navy that isn't enough isn't
even sufficient to
patrol our immense uh
naval boundaries our navy's strength is
not enough to patrol the entirety of our
coast
so it's not it's basically nothing more
than a glorified coast guard through no
fold of its own
it's because india's governments over
decades have
have neglected the navy they have failed
to invest in
building a navy that befits a nation of
india's size
that is the situation india has how many
submarines 14 15 17
north korea has more than 50 submarines
a small little country like north korea
has
three times or more submarines than
india does i mean there is a ridiculous
situation that we are in
to safeguard our national interests we
need to have a strong navy
and we keep repeating the slogan that uh
that the indian ocean region is india's
strategic backyard
well it doesn't become your strategic
backyard with the power of slogans you
have to do something to achieve that
what india needs to do is invest very
strongly in a powerful navy
a navy that can defend its long-term
national interests
it's not about bullying others or
expanding into other people's
territories it's about defending india's
national interest
long-term national interest so india
needs to significantly
boost its naval strength and if india
were to achieve that if india has a
powerful navy
then it can use the indian ocean region
to make the chinese behave in the north
because if india is in a position to
choke off the malacca strait
which would choke off all supplies to
china then china would be forced to
retreat and stop playing mischief in the
north in the india tibet border region
so india should be investing in a
powerful navy
and unfortunately as of now it's not
happening i am hopeful that
india will do that in the future so that
is the way forward
india has always been a maritime nation
india needs to take inspiration from its
history
and reclaim its long-term national
interest
by bolstering the navy many fold much
more than what it is today
so that's a great question
shashank asks what's the future of
afghanistan after the nato withdrawal
can there possibly can there be a
possibility of another civil war
and would there be any spillover in
india
so the future of afghanistan
after the nato withdrawal is that
afghanistan will fall under the chinese
influence
it's already being worked out in
behind the scenes there's going to be a
great deal of chinese influence
there will be some russian influence and
that pakistanis will get some crumbs
they may be allowed to have the taliban
run parts of the country
and so on but it's overall advantage
china
the chinese have been conducting
negotiations between the taliban
and the pakistanis and the russians are
also involved and these countries are
going to decide the
the immediate uh fate of afghanistan
at least in the short term so
afghanistan is not going to
benefit from nato withdrawal
uh it's going to fall under chinese
hands by proxy not overtly but by
by proxy the taliban probably will
serve as a proxy for the chinese like
they used to serve
as a proxy for the pakistanis and that
pakistanis will be kept happy by the by
the chinese
and russia also is involved in certain
ways
russia is getting involved in this
region in pakistan as well as
afghanistan
so that is the immediate future for
afghanistan will there be a civil war
absolutely not
there will be some spurts or bursts of
violence
you know some some shows of violence by
the taliban
to show that we are we are in control
but overall the chinese do not want
any deteriorated deterioration of the
situation they want things to be
stable so that they can start mining
afghanistan and extracting its resources
like the like there are these ancient uh
buddhist
sites which are sitting on enormous
deposits of copper mess ainak
or something like that that's the name
if i recall it correctly
so the chinese want to extract exploit
these natural resources that afghanistan
has to offer
and that's what they're going to start
doing once the americans get out
of afghanistan so that is the immediate
uh
course of action that we are going to
see very soon
and the russians will also take some of
it so that
is the immediate future for afghanistan
there will not be any civil war
and there will most likely not be any
spillover in india
in 1989 or thereabouts when the russians
when the ussr withdrew from afghanistan
there was a spillover into india and the
entire kashmir conflict exploded
and the indian government just sat and
watched and did nothing
this time we have a very different
government the pakistanis know that if
any misadventure happens
things will escalate from our side so i
do not foresee any spillover into india
nothing overt at least there may be some
small upsurge
in certain events but i don't see any
real spillover into india the real loss
for india will be the loss of everything
it has invested
into afghanistan india has been
investing billions of dollars into
rebuilding afghanistan
and and and bringing afghanistan back on
its feet
after the terrors the horrors it has
experienced
all of that is going to be is going to
most likely go to waste if
this happens so the thing is india is
not able to
to influence it's it's near abroad
afghanistan is essentially our near
abroad it's our ancient territory
the the people of afghanistan are the
same ethnicity as us
and india has tried to
to try and help them but as you can see
the
efforts are not sufficient thus far
so in the in the future will india do
some uh do something else to try and
reclaim to regain some sort of
influence in afghanistan that's what
needs to be seen
i hope that we are able to prevent a
complete chinese takeover of afghanistan
but as of now india is not in a
situation to immediately do any of that
so immediately in the next few in the in
the next few years afghanistan is going
to become
a chinese satellite that's how i see it
happen
right next question
gagan asks what is the probability of a
nuclear holocaust
the probability of a nuclear holocaust
is minimal
see even during the cold war when
tensions were at
an incredibly high pitch from time to
time
the united states and the russians never
ever uh actually went to war
there was never a hot war there was
never a single missile launch and the
only time
nuclear weapons have been used was
during the second world war at the end
in hiroshima and nagasaki so nuclear
weapons are essentially
a form of deterrence it says that if you
mess with me i'm going to destroy you
but it's mutually assured destruction to
the most part when you have
two powers that are equal or near equal
in strength
or even if one power even if one country
is only 20 nukes
it is still too big of a risk to
to really uh to cross its red lines
and even somebody like kim jong-un who
is now
the owner of a bunch of nuclear weapons
he's portrayed by the western media as a
crackpot as a crazy person but he's not
he's not nobody is crazy enough to
actually use nuclear weapons
in the in in a conflict not unless
everything is going to be lost then they
may
if if they have nothing to lose they may
use nuclear weapons
but that eventually eventuality is
extremely
unlikely nuclear weapons are only
a means of deterrence and the
probability of a nuclear holocaust is
very remote
that is what i hope at least that is
what i foresee
the real thing the real conflicts are
going to be
below a certain threshold the most of
the conflicts in the future will be
non-kinetic
especially between great powers so the
probability of a nuclear holocaust of
nuclear war is in my opinion
very less
saurabh asks it is very stupid to ask
this but i could not find any other
place so
uh kindly discuss the breaking of the
ussr its reasons
who is responsible for this and its
effect on indian politics and world
politics
no it is not a stupid question by any
means it's a great question
and uh so let's deal with this why did
the ussr
break up so it broke up in the early
1990s i think
um 91 or thereabouts but
the process of the breakup happens
started much
before that so the cold war between the
united states
between the western bloc and the eastern
bloc
that is between the united states and
its allies nato
and between the ussr and its allies the
so-called soviet bloc
this conflict was an ideological
conflict
it was about which system is better
which system is superior
the western uh quasi-liberal
quasi-democratic
capitalistic system or the soviet
socialistic system which system was
better which system was superior
it was an ideological conflict and
what the soviets did after stalin's
deaths after nikita khrushchev came to
power
was they started making uh
pronouncements like
we are not like basically they were to
some extent admitting that their system
had problems
so nikita khrushchev did that uh
brenda did that and then
uh mikhail gorbachev started this
policy of perestroika and glasnost which
was
more openness more transparency and more
self-criticism
so essentially what happened was that
their standing
among their allies and even among their
own people
started to crumble it started to fall
that the
moral high ground and ideological
superiority
that marxism and communism had held and
they saw and that the so the soviet
communist party had held
it started crumbling and mikhail
gorbachev
is one of the main architects of this
by his policies of perestroika and
glasnost so some people said that he was
he was a western mole
in the ussr so we don't know how true or
false it is but his actions
eventually precipitated what happened in
the early 90s when all the
other soviet republics the central asian
republics etc they all declared
independence because
over time because of this perestroika
and glassness
policies the communist party lost
power gradually the power eroded away
and then these republics were emboldened
enough to declare independence from the
ussr
and the ussr broke up overnight so this
was all
engineered gradually step by step
iteratively
by the west by the united states and
they succeeded in the early 90s
so that is why the ussr broke up it was
a great success
on the part of the united states and
then they were able to
to install someone like uh like yeltsin
who was not a very good leader
and under whose regime the us the
the russian nation basically declined to
to a very
to a very poor state and it's when uh
vladimir putin came to power that he
restored gradually
the power of the russian military
so today even though russia is not even
among the top 10 economies in the world
it's most likely either number one or
number two in the most powerful
militaries in the world even the
americans don't really want to mess with
the russians
and they are developing more technology
and much more powerful weapons
all the time so that's why the ussr
crumbled
it was all engineered slowly steadily
gradually by the west
and the policies of mikhail gorbachev
perestroika and glasnost were the last
straw which broke
the dam so that's why it broke up
and after it broke up it did have an
effect on india
india was lost india lost its great
benefactor
and the russian nation that emerged out
of the ussr's ruins
had a very different approach towards
india it was no longer
the same kind of benefactory beneficial
uh partner it was more it was more
pragmatic and realistic and it was not
inclined to support india and everything
so india and russia have slowly drifted
apart india's
diplomats were lost there still even
today some of them are still
mired in this cold war mindset so these
things need to change so it had a great
deal of impact on world politics the
whole
polarity of the world changed the world
became unipolar for quite some time
only one superpower was left the united
states and now we can say that there is
a new superpower on the horizon which is
china
so things changed a lot after the
breakup of the ussr it had a great deal
of
repercussions the world over so that's a
great question
okay om asks what are my thoughts on
terrorism and countries such as russia
and america that are supporting them
sometimes and are against them sooner or
later
why are we still in the 21st century
having to prepare for war all the time
see one has to prepare for wall all the
time if you aren't ready for war you
will never have peace it's only by
preparing for all eventualities that you
can have lasting peace
that is the lesson of history that's
what history has told us
it's what history teaches us teaches us
if you examine the history of the past
two thousand or five thousand years
if you are always in a state of
readiness for war
that is when you will have lasting peace
now about
terrorism you are right america and
uh even the russians have had a very
ambiguous
stand against terrorism so when in 1989
onwards this
terrorism pakistani terrorism started in
kashmir the americans kept dismissing
his
it as a law and order problem it's an
internal matter of law and order you
guys are not taking care of your law and
order
they refused to countenance the truth
which was that pakistan was infiltrating
terrorists into
in large numbers into kashmir so they
did not support they were very much
basically tolerant of terrorism then
when 9 11 happened their stance changed
180 degrees and they became
they launched this global war on terror
and yet they did not ever
sanction pakistan for its continuing
terrorism into india
so it's always been a dual approach and
the same goes with russia they also
sometimes supported some forms of
terrorism what you could call terrorism
sometimes they have not the americans
are
involved in the middle east for for ages
and they do support certain outfits and
certain factions that
can be considered to be terrorist
outfits so it's a
it's a very ambiguous stand and to
understand
why it is so we have to understand what
is the natural interest of the united
states and what is the long-term
objective
that's all they are simply pursuing
their own national interests
they are doing what is best for them
they are trying to achieve their
objectives so sometimes they will
support one group
that other times they will destroy that
group they they propped up saddam
hussein for a very long time
and eventually they destroyed the
damascene right so it's not
it's not an ambiguous policy they are
simply looking out for their best
interests
and interests change situations change
and when circumstances change you take
different actions so that's what happens
there is there is no such thing as
ethics and morality
in geopolitics the only thing that
matters is the hard national interest
and what you intend to do in the long
run and you will do that you you want to
achieve that by any means possible
and that's what we see so that is why
there is this ambiguous stand on
terrorism
sometimes you support it sometimes you
fight it so it's all about
pursuing your long term objectives and
strengthening
your national interest
akash asks democrats or republicans
who have historically been more friendly
with india
so right now the perception is that the
democrats are not friendly with india at
all they are very anti-india and that
that perception is correct but
historically how's it been
right so when india became independent
in 1947
i think it was harry truman who was in
power
who was the president of the united
states in in 1945 he became president he
was a democrat
and it was while he was the president a
democrat
that the united states offered india a
place
a permanent place in this in the
security council in the united nations
security council
the united states made india the offer
on a platter
we are offering you a permanent place on
the united nations security council
and they did this together with russia
so america and russia both made this
offer to india
so the democrats did this
but our great prime minister mr uh
jawaharlal nehru declined
he said that we don't want this we you
need to put china first
we cannot do this unless china is first
given its rightful position in the world
so mr nehru declined this offer and he
said please put china
first in the united nations security
council then in 1955
when uh dwight eisenhower was the
president of the united states he was a
republican
the united states and russia again
offered india
a permanent position on the united
nations security council
and once again mr nehru shari jawala
nehru refused
he said not at the cost of china
and mr nehru ensured that china became a
permanent
member of the of this united nations
security council india still
is not in that position
so we lost the opportunity so a democrat
offered it first
then a republican offered offer the same
thing then
when john f kennedy became the president
of the united states
in 1961 he offered
india he offered to transfer nuclear
technology to india
he offered this to jawaharlal nehru he
wanted india to be
an american ally against countries such
as china
and russia so he offered to transfer
full-scale nuclear weapons technology to
india
and our great prime minister nehru
declined he said that we
are not interested in war we are a
peaceful nation
and then 1962 happened so john f kennedy
was a democrat
so historically republicans as well as
democrats were
very positively inclined towards india
they offered a great deal to india
india always rebuffed them and that's
when americans the americans understood
that india
does not intend to be
a nation of any significance of any kind
so they turned their backs off
on india they started cultivating
pakistan
and under nixon they started cultivating
china as well
and so india by its own doing but the
doing of its great prime minister mr
nehru
india became reduced to a geopolitical
backwater of the world
now today it is true that the democrats
are very much
more anti-india than the republicans
that's a that's a pattern that we see
for a very long time
even uh bill clinton was very much anti
india
so even when bill clinton was the
president of the united states it was
very much
an anti-india kind of regime so that's
uh
that's a pattern that we see over the
over the past few decades
but at the very beginning both parties
were
they they both tried to engage india in
a very positive and constructive manner
and it's only because of mr nehru's
idealism
and and and
his desire to be a a great moral
statesman that
this situation eventually happened so
that's the answer to this question
biswaru bhattacharji asks
what can india do to become a superpower
and which country is the best biggest
friend i will answer question number one
what can india do to become a superpower
so one cannot learn
how to sprint before one learns how to
jog
and one cannot learn how to jog before
one learns how to walk properly
so india is currently learning how to
walk that is where we are at
so we must not have oversized ambitions
today
i understand that we have waited long
enough
that now we are a more a slightly more
prosperous nation
and we are our young people are full of
ambition full of vitality
full of energy and they can't understand
why india is
in the situation that it is today why is
india will
not recognize the great power
the first thing is india should ditch
its obsession
with soft power there is no such thing
as soft power soft power
is worthless without hard power a
superpower can never be a soft
superpower
it's always a hard superpower so let me
explain the difference
between soft power and hard power let's
say i have
a hundred thousand followers on twitter
so they will listen to me when i tweet
something they will look at it they may
like it they will retweet it
and if i offer some opinion then they
may consider it
and they may take it seriously or they
may ignore it so at least i am
being heard i have some
sort of influence on a hundred thousand
people that
is soft power a little bit of influence
now what is hard power let's say that i
have
a hundred highly trained soldiers who
are heavily armed
with the latest weapons and they will
obey me instantaneously without question
that is hard power what does the world
respect
it respects hard power what can effect
change in the world
hard power you cannot affect soft
changes in the world unless you have
the backing of hard power if you have
the fallback of going back to hard power
if soft power doesn't work that is when
soft power
is effective so india needs to develop
hard power now what is hard power in the
geopolitical sense
firstly economy but economy is also
worthless unless you have a strong
military
you can have the greatest culture and
economy in the world and you can be the
richest country in the world
you can have one third of the entire
world gdp but if you don't have a strong
military
it is all pointless so to become
a superpower india needs to step by step
by step
take baby steps start bolstering its
military
not for the sake of expanding into other
people's territories but for the sake of
protecting and investing in its own
national interests
so the most important thing is to have a
powerful navy and a powerful air force
and to invest in the latest technologies
we cannot have a five million strong
army
equipped with 1980s machine guns we need
to invest in robotics we need to
invest in artificial intelligence cyber
warfare space warfare the latest
technologies for the sake of the gods
so these are the things that india needs
to do india needs to embrace
science and technology in order to
eventually someday become a superpower
it is never too late we have all the
talent in the world
we have the most intelligent young boys
and girls in the world
please leverage this incredible
god-gifted
talent so that's what india needs to do
to become
a superpower so that is uh
the final question out of the
pre-selected questions let me now take a
look
at some of your chat questions are you
asking me something interesting
i will take up a few questions
okay one second let me remove this
so we know that china is expansionary
ambitious to become a superpower
respects its native language
it industrialized at pace it spends on
research and technology
but aren't these our drawbacks to work
on absolutely correct absolutely spot-on
there is a lot that india can learn from
the chinese they
have self-respect they follow their own
laws
they don't look upon the west for
inspiration they don't have a
constitution there is copy pasted from
the west
they don't have laws that were left over
by the british they do not hate their
own culture
right india's constitution is a is a
mishmash of copy pasted contents from
the
from the west india's laws are still the
british laws
we are simply copy some modifying some
laws
the entire indian legal system is
british
all our institutions are british so we
are still fully colonized
right i mean i have to speak in english
that half the country can understand me
that is the situation we are in the
chinese have self-respect
india's leadership has zero self-respect
india's
ministry of external affairs gives
briefings news
briefings in english the chinese give
them in chinese
so that is the difference so there is a
lot we can learn from the chinese
they respect their native language they
have always
invested in science and technology and
education you invest in education you're
investing in the future generations
so you need to have a good education
system india's education system is
rotten to the core
so there is a lot that we can learn from
china
women one may not be a big fan of the
chinese but there is a lot to respect
them for and a lot to learn from them
the chinese communist party is an
extremely ambitious organism it has a
great deal of vision
and it has a single-minded pursuit of
what it seeks and that's what
makes it so successful so yes india can
learn
a few things from the chinese i agree
okay let me find some more questions
thank you mr president even if we defeat
and capture pakistan how do we deal
relica de radicalize such huge radical
population
should we adopt the ccp's way of dealing
with the uighurs and xinjiang
okay you will appoint me as my future
special advisor
i am against any kind of forcible
uh changes of culture it has to happen
naturally it has to take its own time if
they want to revert to their
indigenous ancestral culture it is a
choice they have to make
we have to remove external influences
and let
nature take its own course india did not
become
very what it is today overnight it took
a thousand years
this is not a sprint this is a marathon
deradicalization is different from
imposing something on somebody
it is not possible to change an entire
nation's culture in 5 years or 10 years
or even 20 years
i believe that india the entire indian
subcontinent should integrate
eventually when the time is right
but it cannot be done it cannot be
rushed it cannot be done overnight
it is a step-by-step process india needs
to have a long-term vision
this is a 100-year marathon so that is
my answer to
answer to this question
okay rohan asked nehru was so fond of
china what did he do when they attacked
us and why was he
so fond of them nahiru was a socialist
that the chinese claimed to be
socialists
that's why he loved them so much nehru
thought he was one of the great
statesmen of the world
and he he believed that mao sajun was
also a great statesman so that's why he
had this admiration for mao
and for china and nehru was he had this
inferiority complex he was a british
educated anglicized anglophilic
kind of guy who did nothing ever to to
come to power he was not
elected the prime minister of india he
was selected the prime minister of india
over the head of sardar patel we know
the history very well
mohandas gandhi armed twisted the
congress party into
appointing nehru instead of patel as the
prime minister even though patel got all
the votes
so nehru did not well he saw himself as
a great statement but statesman but he
did not have
any significant leadership qualities
and he took us down the wrong path and
much of what
ails us today is thanks to his uh
thanks to his policies
okay let me see some more
where would india have to
okay chaitanya asks where would india
have to start to build its defense
lands air and sea into a scale which
would make us the owners and keepers of
our waters
we have to start by investing in our own
industries we have
the scientists and the engineers and the
talented people that we need
we can build everything on our own we
can build our own weaponry
our own systems our own aircraft our own
submarines our own ships
we can do it all on our own we need to
stop importing from outside
we need to have a concentrated effort in
bolstering
defense industries that's the first step
and then we need to start
allocating sufficient amount of funds
to produce this weaponry we need to
restructure the armed forces
in a way that is the most efficient
possible
currently the armed forces are still
outdated the the
structuring the command structure is not
the most efficient as of now through no
fold of the armed forces
it is the bureaucracy that has imposed
this strangled hold
on the armed forces if you allow the
armed forces to do it on their own they
would do a much
much better job but it is the
politicians and the bureaucrats who
control all the decisions
so these are some of the problems there
are some fundamental problems we have to
solve
but the main thing is diff build your
own defense industries restructure the
armed forces in the most logical and
streamlined fashion
and invest money in building up the navy
and the air force
quantity has a quality all of its own
you don't need to buy f-22s and f-35s
even if you have 1000 pages fighters
which cost
hardly anything it can overwhelm any on
any air force in the world
it's all about utilizing what you have
whatever advantages you have and
maximizing those advantages
so that's what india should do in my
opinion
okay let's see some more
anantam asks why isn't the world doing
anything against china
we gave china religion and trade and
they gave us war and expansionary views
please talk about this there is this uh
pancho tantra or jataka tale right that
that if you if you feed a snake it's not
gonna repave
you with gratitude it's gonna it's gonna
bite you back
that's the answer and why is the world
not doing anything because the chinese
have infiltrated every
institution in the world the united
nations the world health organization
they have bought over the western media
they have bought over hollywood so
everyone is quiet
as simple as that they have bribed all
the little dictators in africa
they have bribed the sri lankan
government they are bribing their way
throughout the world
so that's why china is able to get its
get its uh things done
and that's why the while that's why the
world is quiet
we gave china everything we gave the
snake milk and now they're biting us
back
we need to introspect about our china
policy that's what needs to be done
you can't blame a serpent for being a
serpent
but you can blame yourself for trusting
a serpent
that's the moral of the story
lokesh asks can we co-exist
with pakistan through the means of art
culture and other means
and is there any similarities between
india and pakistan
you see lokesh india and pakistan are
the same country
they're the same people we have the same
ancestry we have the same
roots it is our land that was given
away without our consent
okay the people of india never agreed to
this land being given away
this is our land it has been illegally
partitioned eventually over time
if not in our lifetime in our
descendants lifetime it will become
again part of the united subcontinent of
united bharat
but that is in the future can we
co-exist with them
through the means of art culture and
other means they don't
follow they don't believe in the same
things that we do their culture is
different right
culturally they are now alien to us they
do not recognize the fact that they
their ancestors were indians they don't
recognize where they come from
they identify more with the arabs
and when they did not work they now they
are not now trying to identify with the
turks
so it is impossible to co-exist with
them on the basis of culture
or art the only thing is we need to
currently have a long-term plan
for re for for ensuring
peace on our borders and to ensure peace
we have to look at china first before
pakistan
pakistan is in no situation to do us any
significant deal amount of harm
the chinese are so our main focus should
be
on defanging the chinese
that should be the main focus right now
okay one more question and then we will
be done
ashwin asks how can india counter the
chinese
string of pearls in the indian ocean the
answer is very simple ashwin
build a strong navy build a strong naval
force and then
the chinese will not be able to
build that stranglehold that they are
constructing right now
okay since okay one final question
this is from rohan why do i feel that
india's major problem is the population
it's more about the quantity than the
quality life our people has here
yes population is a major problem it is
not a demographic dividend it's a
demographic disaster if it continues
like this
india needs to find ways of of slowing
down its population growth
the most effective way of slowing
population growth is to
have better quality of life look at any
developed country
the population growth is always low the
the fertility
rate is always low in a highly developed
country it's only in the poor countries
that the fertility rate is very high so
the moment you your your standards of
living increase
and you become more prosperous the need
to have 50 children
goes away so what india needs to do is
yes definitely control its population
bring it under control but not
drastically like the chinese have done
the chinese are facing a genuine
demographic disaster
the majority of that population will be
elderly very soon
and the people of china live strange
ridiculous lives
they don't have cousins they don't have
brothers they don't have sisters they
don't have anchors they don't have ants
these are very strange lives these
people live this is an artificially
truncated
and and mangled society
and that that's the cause of some of the
social problems you have in china
so india needs to do it judiciously
population is
a significant problem over population i
mean
but we cannot drastically reduce the
population by any means we should never
do that
let it come down gradually organically
naturally
and we need to have the right policies
in place to do this
all right thank you everybody this was a
wonderful discussion
some great questions i will do this
again and we'll take some more
interesting questions about geopolitics
but for tonight
it is the end so i will see you tomorrow
same time thank you everybody
have a great night have a great day bye